Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Hi, I'm Chris Van Hollen. I want to thank all of you who are joining this conversation today on a very important topic, which is the long-term unemployed. And I'm really pleased that we're joined here today by two individuals who have devoted themselves to helping working people, especially those who have been most left out.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): We're joined by Mark Morial and Melissa Young. Mark Morial has been a real friend for a long time and somebody who's been in the trenches and leading the fight as the president of the National Urban League. And as I think everyone knows, the National Urban League has been at the forefront of the fight for...
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): people who are living in urban
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): areas, and especially those who have been left out in so many ways from economic progress. So it's wonderful to have Marc Morial here. Melissa Young has also worked with us on legislation to address these issues, and she is the Senior Director of Research and Policy at the Heartland Alliance, which is one of our nation's leading anti-poverty organizations.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): It's great to have you both here. As we know, long-term unemployment was a real problem even before the pandemic. And long-term unemployment
Speaker 3: really refers to people who have been looking for work for more than six months and unable to find a job.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): And the more time goes on, we know the harder it is for them to get back in the workforce.
And
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): there were over a million people who were in that category before the pandemic. But now we've seen record numbers of people join the ranks of the long-term unemployed. So it is now up to 3.5 million of our fellow Americans. And the challenge here is to make sure that as the economy recovers, that we bring these individuals into the workforce so they don't remain locked
out.
And
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): that's why we're really grateful that both of you worked with us, with Senator Ron White and myself, to form the legislation called the Long-Term
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Unemployment Elimination Act. And appreciate your really leading us in this conversation here. So I'd just like to
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): start, Mark, with you. And if you could talk about,
in the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): context of this pandemic.
We
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): know on the healthcare front, it's had a disproportionate impact on communities
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): of color. We've also seen that same harmful impact on the economic front. So talk a little
Speaker 4: bit about why the economic pain is falling so disproportionately in certain communities. So,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Senator, thank you so very much for doing this and for your fight and work on the legislation. Melissa, great to be with you and thank you for your energy and effort.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Think about the pandemic and think about the impact it's had. So you're a worker for, I'll use it,
American or United Airlines. And
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): all of a sudden, the pandemic
Speaker 6: hits, travel slows, and you're laid off. And you've been, and this is a tragedy of it, you've been stably
employed.
for a
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): long, long period of
time. What is
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the impact? Maybe you can collect unemployment for a short period of time but not indefinitely.
That for
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): which you are trained is work that has basically gone away across the board.
You're on the edge of foreclosure. You
Speaker 7: become food insecure.
or if
Speaker 7: you're a renter, you're on the edge of eviction. And the human
Speaker 6: toll that it takes, I have found that for those who become long-term unemployed after a period of employment where they've been used to being stably
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): employed, it's an embarrassment.
It
Speaker 7: is a pride buster. It is a creates
and
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): psychological and emotional pressure. We've got to understand that many of the long-term unemployed, particularly in this environment, are not there because they want to be there. And think about the profile. So in that sector, the service sector, hotels, hospitality, restaurants, eating establishments,
Speaker 6: those jobs are disproportionately
Speaker 6: black and brown. They're also disproportionately women with children, young women with children. And sometimes there's a stereotype
that the
Speaker 7: long-term unemployed is a shiftless,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): unmotivated person looking for some place
to hang.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): And we've got to paint
Speaker 7: the picture
Speaker 7: that the
Speaker 6: long-term unemployed are people who are the backbone of communities and find themselves. And in some instances, they also become long-term unemployed because the factory, the job, the business that they work for has moved
on and
Speaker 6: changed. And the new jobs,
they're not prepared
Speaker 6: for. They're not trained for. And it's easy to say to
a
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): 40-year-old,
"Hey,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): why don't you go get some training?
Why don't
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): you go learn?" And the 40-year-old says, "I'm a very competent, hardworking, skilled worker."
What do
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): you mean? I got to go spend $10,000 and go to community college?
Go to
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): school, get a credential, go take
a
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): bunch of classes? And if I do that, am I guaranteed? So we have to, in this
instance, I
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): think it's important.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): There are many, many, I've used a few examples.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): of who may be long-term unemployed, but think about it. A person in the restaurant business or in the hospitality business or working at a hotel may have been laid off in March
and they're still
Speaker 9: out of work.
They're still
Speaker 9: out of work and they're looking
and
Speaker 6: they've got to not only find the job, they've got to find a job in this market where they
are,
they
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): have family, they have roots, they may have responsibilities.
So we've
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): gotta, you know, really,
really understand. And
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): that's why what you're doing to provide response and relief to it is so important. But I, it's a battle, Senator and Melissa, to disavow the stereotypes.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): There are people who don't want to work, but to suggest that that's the main or that's the majority is cruel and unusual.
It is
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): absolutely cruel and unusual.
I
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): think we need, as you say, to be doing two things right now during this pandemic. You know, for everybody that's been thrown out of work or lost their job because of the pandemic, we've got to extend that emergency unemployment insurance, which expires at the end of this month. That is
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): essential. And then as we work to rebuild the economy and we have the vaccines deployed,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): I'm worried about all the people you're talking about right now, Mark, falling behind, right? The stock market looks good. The economy looks like it's coming back in terms of growth. But this long-term unemployment number could be very sticky unless we all work together to make sure that we provide opportunities.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): What is the challenge here and what kind
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): of things are we going to need to do to make sure that this long-term unemployment challenge doesn't become even worse?
Speaker 11: Yeah, well, first, thank you so much, Senator, for your leadership in this space. It's been an absolute joy to work with you on this legislation and other things. And Mark, for this opportunity, it's wonderful to be with you tonight. I
think
Speaker 12: one of the things I've been thinking about a lot with COVID is that in
Speaker 13: many ways, and Mark, you articulated it and gave some stories that I think are just so critical to
Speaker 13: To what I've been talking about and thinking about taking off the rose-colored
Speaker 14 (higher-pitched voice): glasses that some folks have been sporting around the strength of our economy, right? And the ways in which our economy, quite frankly, doesn't work for everyone, right? And what we're doing and what we have done, we cannot repeat.
Speaker 14 (higher-pitched voice): right? I mean, the data bears this out, which we talked about. The numbers of individuals filing for unemployment insurance, it continues to go up. The numbers of women leaving the labor market, in fact, many of those women largely being Black women. The numbers of youth who are unemployed reaching
Speaker 14 (higher-pitched voice): Absolutely staggering numbers. And those are
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): policy choices, right? Those are not anomalies. They're not accidents. They are policy
Speaker 14 (higher-pitched voice): choices. This is something that we can fix, right? And so when I think about, you know, the challenges that our participants at Heartland Alliance face or other challenges that participants and individuals face in getting into the labor
Speaker 17 (higher-pitched voice): market,
Speaker 18: getting back into the
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): labor market, the first thing, and Mark raised this, is that people want to work. And we need to disavow that myth immediately. Secondly, is that what stands
in the
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): way of people getting back into the labor market are the very things that make it so that each of us, many of us, can actually go to work, right? It's having adequate transportation, right, when we need it, or having access to good jobs
that pay
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): enough to keep a stable roof over our heads and food on the table. And so that we don't need to make a choice between paying our rent or our mortgage and turning on and keeping the lights on, right? I mean, these are ways that people can access good jobs and stay in good jobs. And I'd be remiss, you know, in this conversation too, to just not, to
Speaker 17 (higher-pitched voice): highlight that, you know,
Speaker 17 (higher-pitched voice): Also, in this country, we bar millions of individuals, hard-working
Speaker 14 (higher-pitched voice): individuals, from getting access to jobs because of what I talk about as the go-go gadget arms of
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): the criminal legal system, right? The arms of our criminal legal system wrap around and reach out to folks long after their involvement in the criminal justice system.
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): to bar
Speaker 17 (higher-pitched voice): access to jobs, oftentimes for a lifetime, right? And so even if the economy recovers, these are challenges that individuals face in communities and many individuals are facing today and have faced long before
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): COVID. So I think one of the things that we have to do when we're talking about economic recovery is build differently, right? We need to build better,
and
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): we need to build differently because it is imperative
Speaker 17 (higher-pitched voice): for our democracy, for communities, for families, for
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): individuals to bring folks from the sidelines back into the labor market.
Well, that's a
Speaker 19: great segue into what I was going to ask because both your
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): organizations have very strong public policy shops where you make important recommendations
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): But you also have service, you know, components to your organizations. And so, Mark,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): in your experience, what are the kind of supports
Speaker 3: that are necessary in order to make sure that these individuals who want to work
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): are able to, you know, we can knock down the barriers so that they're able to enter the workforce?
-
Speaker 20: Of course.
- I just,
Speaker 20: I love
the
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): people programs that we run at the National
Urban League,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): because it's where you can see a difference
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): made in a person's life.
And the way our
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): work evolves is that it's based on an individual assessment and an
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): individual plan.
So if all
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): three of us walked in, my plan may look different than yours. It may look different than Melissa's. It's going to be tailored according to my skills, my aspirations, my desires, my abilities. And then what do
I need to get
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): from point A to point B? So, you
know, if
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): we need to help someone because they've got an alcohol and drug issue, we're going to do that. If they have low literacy and they need
help,
GED,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): we're going to do that. If they're ready for employment from a skills base, but they have soft skills issues, we
have soft
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): skills programs. So just trying to work directly with people, and we work to put people in tech jobs, we work to put people in hospitality jobs, construction jobs, lots of tech work now, but it's basically based on
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the market where the program operates? Where are the opportunities? And I'm a big believer in pragmatic preparation. Let's prepare people for something that's real,
not
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): something that's imaginable. Let's prepare. They want to work. They want to earn money. They don't want to just say, I know how to do
X, Y, and Z. And so
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): I think it's a really critical
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): part of these direct services. But let me make this point about
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): direct services programs and Senator, I've made this point before committees in the house over the years. And that is people say, well, if you have all these great programs,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): why do we have long-term unemployed and poverty? I said, scale, man, scale. I got a great program re-entry program in Chicago. I served 50 people. Okay, 50
people
Speaker 21: in a six-month
cycle.
How many
Speaker 21: people need it, 2,000, 3,000? I said, it's scale. We think when
it
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): comes to investments in people, in programs that help people get out of poverty, we never want to think in terms of scale.
We want
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): to think in terms of pilots, and we want to think in terms of demonstration projects, and we
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): want to think in terms of initiatives, and we don't want to think in terms of scale. And I think some scaling
is
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): what's necessary. We know, Melissa, you know what works. You know it works. We know it works and we have evidence that it works. But its scale is not wide enough and large enough to have, to move the needle in the way we need to move the needle. The final thing I'll say, and I think this is important. I just
have a
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): hard time understanding the need.
Why a
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): country with such an enormity of wealth,
Speaker 24: goodwill, human talent would tolerate poverty? Why
would you
Speaker 24: tolerate high levels of poverty?
Why would
Speaker 24: you disinvest in the great
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): American urban metropolises, big and small, in America?
Yeah.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): when they're what we're known for.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): We're known for New York and Baltimore and Philadelphia and Chicago. And we're known for smaller communities like Macon and Springfield. The
Speaker 6: world knows us. The world may not know Illinois, they sure know Chicago. They may not know Pennsylvania,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): but they know the city
of brotherly love.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): And so it is important.
to
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): understand that we have to invest in those communities to a
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): greater extent than we have. And hopefully in this environment, Senator, notwithstanding some of the opposition you and I referenced before we joined the air tonight, we have to press. We have to push and understand
Speaker 25: that this is not, what we're talking about is not left or right. It's common sense. That's
Speaker 26: right. Yep. Yeah. Yeah, 100%.
It
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): is totally common sense and as you say,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): the failure to make, to ensure, the failure to ensure that we have
Speaker 3: vibrant cities
is a
Speaker 3: choice because there are things we can be doing right
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): now to help change that in dramatic ways.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): And you raised the issue of scale, and so that really does bring us to this next question here because, you know, we can have successful grant programs, and I know both of your organizations have them, but as you just said, Mark, you could be helping 50 people with a grant program. But to do this at scale, I do believe we need significant federal resources.
And
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): I'm going to ask Melissa, but I just want to I always remember that in 2008, during the, you know, economic meltdown when we had the economic recovery bill, one of the programs
Speaker 3: was to help federal funds to help subsidize jobs. And Haley Barber.
Speaker 27: That's right.
Speaker 3: Mississippi.
Speaker 3: I remember that champion that program. He said, this works.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): So maybe Melissa, can you talk about, you know, taking this to scale and the role the federal government can play?
Speaker 28: Yeah, I remember. It's so funny. So you just triggered all kinds of memories, because in the over the Christmas holiday, going from
Speaker 11: 08 to 09, I was writing part of that RL legislation that included some of that those subsidized employment components. So you just
Speaker 11: Yeah. And
Speaker 13: it's true. We saw these programs be implemented across the country, putting about 260 or so thousand folks into jobs in red states, in blue states, because as you
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): said, Senator, it's common sense, right? I think one of the things that a key lesson that we learned from the Great Recession is that the private sector is not going to generate the new jobs that we need to make a full recovery.
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): and adequately address quality jobs as well,
Speaker 13: right? And I think so when we think about what the power of jobs programs at the federal level, we need to be able to expand the quantity of good jobs and the quality of jobs. And, you know, I've been
Speaker 14 (higher-pitched voice): talking about this a lot with folks
about,
I
Speaker 14 (higher-pitched voice): think this begins to come down to using all of the mechanisms that we have at the federal
Speaker 13: government to
make a
Speaker 13: commitment to economic justice in the Biden-Harris administration. And that really flows through all parts of the administration.
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): But I'm glad, Mark, that you talked a little bit about scale. I think, you know, there's a scope, scale and duration issue, right? One of the things we learned in the Great Recession
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): That a lot of these jobs programs that were putting people back to work, that were good for business, that were good for
Speaker 13: communities, that were good for taxpayers, right, ended too soon before folks were able to make a full recovery. So I think that is something that should stick with us,
Speaker 17 (higher-pitched voice): right? Not only scope and scale, but duration. And also, you know, we know that these programs and we also know that the federal government has the power to eliminate.
Speaker 17 (higher-pitched voice): barriers
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): that prevent folks from accessing these jobs, right, or getting a foothold in the jobs in the first place. And I hope, you know, I've been talking a little bit about building differently, but I think we have this opportunity as we think about the future of some of these subsidized employment programs and as we think towards the future of this legislation and others, to build differently by co-creating with communities who have been economically marginalized And really doubling down and saying, what is it
that you need
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): need and want? How can we, through the federal government,
Speaker 14 (higher-pitched voice): build economically vibrant community through these subsidized employment programs? And so I think we have an opportunity.
Speaker 29: You
Speaker 9: know, our chief economics advisor, Dr. Bernard Anderson,
Professor
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Emeritus from the Wharton School, a labor economist, former Assistant Secretary of Labor
for Bill Clinton, has
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): pounded into my head since 2008 the notion of public service jobs
Speaker 30: yeah and
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): has
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): said repeatedly that
it is
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): one of the most powerful stimulus initiatives you can undertake because these folks are going to spend 70% of them their earnings right back in that's
Speaker 31: right through
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): the economy and
you
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): know we advanced
in the
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): early days of Obama, we couldn't get any real traction on it, a public service jobs initiative, which would have allowed public service jobs to be placed at universities, community colleges, city governments, state agencies, and cultural facilities, you know, art museums, et cetera, et cetera. And we couldn't get, and you know, I think it
was,
You
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): know, the thinking has to do with the stereotypes and cynicism. Sure. Somehow people, you know, want
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): to, people are looking for nothing, something for nothing. And, you know, so many of these
folks are mothers. Right.
Speaker 21: They're
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): moms. That's right. And in our experience, and you talked a little bit about it, Mark, too, in our experience, when
we offer an
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): opportunity for
folks
Speaker 13: to work, they take it over and over again, right? They take it. When you offer a low barrier opportunity to work, folks are like, yes, yes.
Speaker 13: That's what I want to do. And I think that that is, that gets at some of this myth, right? And we can look at almost every single evaluation of these kinds of programs dating back way, way, way,
Speaker 34: way back.
Speaker 13: Right? You give somebody an opportunity to work and they take it. And so I'm with you. Like, let's just, like, debunk
Speaker 35: that. Like, let's put that on
Speaker 36: self, you know?
And I think we have to...
You
Speaker 37: know, Senator Van Hollen is in a great position because as a champion of this,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): you know, these types of things get funded through, you know, large scale stimulus, omnibus recovery type acts where people look and where multiple things can
get
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): embedded. I think it, you know, it's, there's a thing. We have to try some new
Speaker 38: things.
Speaker 39: Yeah. Yeah.
Speaker 39: See, at the end of the day, there's an insanity continuing to do the same damn thing and looking for another
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): result. And that does bring me to the last question here and, you know, both of you and your organizations have worked on this legislation and, you know, to Melissa's point and your point, Mark, doing
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): programs just
Speaker 3: in response to an emergency, if they're not sustained, then they're not durable. You need
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): the duration component to go with this. It can't just be a flash in the pan. It's true that it's important to help people in an emergency, but the whole
Speaker 3: issue with long-term unemployment is...
is
Speaker 3: that it's an ongoing chronic problem and these are people who want to work, as you say, by definition, in order to say you're unemployed, you have to be looking for work. There are a lot more people who are not long-term unemployed
who were,
Speaker 3: who fell out of the workforce because they got discouraged and we'd like to bring them back
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): in too.
And
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): that's why we think we need this sort of quantum change, this big change that you're talking about, Mark, with this bill. And it would call for substantial,
Speaker 3: essentially, you know, job sharing costs. The federal government would help subsidize the cost of employment. When unemployment rates are low all around the country, it would be a two-thirds match. This is over a two-year period. The idea is, as we say, people want a chance.
Speaker 3: They want to get into the workforce, they want a job, we're going to provide some financial help to employers to hire them, whether they're in the private sector or public sector or nonprofit sector,
and provide
Speaker 3: the supports, you know, you got to be able to get transportation to get to work. You need to make sure that we knock down the barriers, but we need a system-wide.
You
Speaker 3: know, Senator,
Speaker 42: I'm thinking that a business sector that
I
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): think could be mobilized to support this might be the airline and hospitality industry because it would be a way to support them getting back on their feet if the government provided subsidies to them as a part
of a
to
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): provide public service jobs for cities and states and non-profits also but if you had an industry who because this what you're talking about is not a loan
not talking about
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): a loan and I think it needs to be
because I
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): think it's worth I have noticed and you
know
-
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Glimmers of that there's a different type
of CEO
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): sitting in the suites of some American businesses now.
They are
Speaker 44: from a different generation. They're not as wedded
to
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): yesterday's thinking. They've got to manage in a pandemic
and they
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): may be open to new and different ways. They may be responsive to an
invitation
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): from you and the president elect to sit around the table and consider some new ideas, if it will benefit their business, if it will benefit them getting back on their feet. It's about finding the right angle and doing it now, but you're right, it needs to be long-term, it needs to be sustainable. And a great nation like ours
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): should not have poverty and long-term unemployment, period.
Speaker 46: Yeah, full stop, full stop, right?
Speaker 13: I mean, I think one of the things that you said, Senator, that, you know, really, I think is so true and also sparked something for me, which is that this isn't a flash-in-the-pan program, right? This is a system.
Speaker 13: And the only way we are going to have transformational kinds of change when we think about things like long-term unemployment is to build systems, right? Because systems behave in exactly the ways that we construct them to behave, right? And so...
Speaker 13: I think that's actually what's so exciting about this piece of legislation is the way that it's structured to address long-term unemployment, to address crises, and also to address what we know are structural barriers to employment, right? Like we've talked about tonight, right? Things like transportation or childcare access or transportation.
You
Speaker 13: know, having a criminal record. Right. And so I think that's really important because that's when you begin
Speaker 16 (higher-pitched voice): to act to make change. Right. And for me, I mean, I'm just sitting and sitting in my seat.
Speaker 13: Right. I mean, like getting people back to work who might be sitting on the sidelines. That's that's good for all of us. Right. That is a fundamentally a bipartisan idea. Right. Let's let's get folks who are on the sideline back to work.
-
Speaker 47: We have to
push
Speaker 47: the needle for you a new way of thinking about economic policy
Speaker 48: that's right
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): this is what we're talking about we've lived through an era where you know it was you know give a little tax incentive do a little something over here it it was it was what i call small bore uh
not big
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): thinking not imaginative thinking not understanding the fundamental of the american economy is consumer spending
And if
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): people have money in their pocket, they will spend money. They will buy groceries. They will pay rent.
They will
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): buy diapers. They will buy a formula. They will go to Bed Bath & Beyond or Costco's or Big Lots or wherever they shop, right? They're going to spend some money. And that's the driver of the economy. So when people are working and they have a job, they also have
pride.
Speaker 49: Dignity, self-worth, standing.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): All of that comes with the job, the ability to
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): support yourself, your loved ones.
Speaker 50: And as we've been saying, the idea behind this legislation is it's system-wide
Speaker 19: change, as Melissa and you have said. It's not
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): just as much...
you
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): know, good on a very localized basis that a grant program can do, this is economy-wide. This is system-wide. This is changing incentives to make sure that people who want to work, but for a whole host of reasons, barriers have been sort of left behind. And the longer they're left
Speaker 3: behind, you
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): know, the harder it is for them to get back up and into the workforce. And so this is designed...
to
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): make sure that we change that dynamic. 'Cause I'm very nervous that as we come out of the pandemic and we begin to recover, we forget all those people who are still long-term unemployed. And I am pleased that in the Biden-Harris administration as part of the economic team, we have a number of folks who have worked with us on this proposal.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Jared Bernstein, Heather, others, and I think they recognize that this is something that we have to do early on in January. We can't leave, it would be unconscionable for the Congress to leave in December without providing people with some lifeboat and safety now.
Speaker 51: But this next measure has to happen early in the next administration.
Speaker 52: It's got to be bold. We have to go fight for it.
Speaker 52: That's right.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): And it's going to take some work. But you see, I think that the public is poised. I mean, when you look at the opinion polling
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): on this, sometimes some members of Congress are so out of touch, right? They're actually time warped.
Yeah. Living in
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): another era. You know,
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): they still think it's the Reagan
era.
That was
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): 40 years ago. They're still dreaming of Ronald Reagan, Arthur
Speaker 47: Laffer, and
I call
Speaker 47: it the laugh curve.
Speaker 53: Yeah, well, it was about worth as much as the napkin was written on. Yeah,
Speaker 54: exactly. Well, let me really thank both of you and your teams and
Speaker 4: organizations
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): for what you're doing to help end poverty in America.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): and make sure that everybody has a chance to make it. I mean, as you say, it's just that kind of common sense, Mark. Let me turn it over to the two of you to make any kind of final comments. Yeah,
Speaker 55: all I'll say, and I'll give Melissa the last word, thanks for having us. And let's just take
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): this, I think, a lot of the goodwill and good discussion today, and let's go see if in January and early February, this is something we can include. I mean, I think we've got to push.
Speaker 56: That's right.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): On on the economic team in the new administration, I think we've got to build some consensus in the Congress around it and and some grassroots support. So I'm committed to working on it with you.
Speaker 57: Yeah.
Speaker 58: Well,
Speaker 59: I'm grateful for for Melissa. Yeah.
Speaker 58: No, I was just going to say cosign on that. And thank you so much for the opportunity.
Speaker 60: I think I think you're right, Mark. I think we've got to push on this. We
we.
Speaker 60: can't continue to do things like we've done, right? Or we're going to have far too many people who can't get access to the labor market long-term, and that's not good for any of us, right? So thank you for your
Speaker 61: support on this, and thank you for your work on this. We look forward to working alongside you. Well,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): thank you both so much, and thank all the folks who have joined us in this conversation. We're going to count on all the folks viewing this to be part of our team pushing to get this over the finish line
Speaker 62: thank you
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): all